A Guide to the Papers of Oscar A. Thorup, Jr., 1956-1997
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Papers of Oscar A. Thorup, Jr. 1956-1997
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-47
6 boxes, 5"x10.5"x15.5," 2.5 feet, 186 folders
Historical Collections
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Dr. and Mrs. Oscar A. Thorup.
Biographical/Historical Information
Oscar A. Thorup, Jr., was born March 12, 1922, in Washington D.C., the son of Pattie Walter Creecy and Oscar A. Thorup. After earning his undergraduate degree in 1944 at the University of Virginia, he graduated from the U.Va. School of Medicine in 1946. He was a member of the Raven Society, Sigma Xi, and Alpha Omega Alpha. He did his internship at Queen's Hospital in Honolulu, Hawai'i, and then spent two years in the Army Medical Corps at Tripler General Hospital, also in Honolulu. He returned to U.Va. in 1949 for his residency training in internal medicine. He was a research fellow for one year at the University of North Carolina where he worked with Dr. Louis Welt on renal function, electrolyte balance, and metabolism.
In 1953 Dr. Thorup returned to U.Va. as an Instructor in Internal Medicine and as head of the Teachers" Preventorium. The next year he received a $30,000, five year grant from the John and Mary R. Markle Foundation which he used to study abnormal hemoglobins. He was also appointed an Assistant to the Dean in 1954 and worked closely with Dr. Thomas H. Hunter. He served as an Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine and Assistant to the Dean starting in 1955 until he was granted a year's leave of absence to be a visiting investigator in Oxford, England, in 1958. He worked with Dr. R. G. MacFarlane and Dr. Alan Sharp at the Radcliffe Infirmary on blood coagulation and continued his studies in abnormal hemoglobin. Before his return to U.Va., Dr. Thorup used a grant from the Rockefeller Foundation to visit medical schools in Scandinavia to assess the feasibility of a staff and student exchange program with his alma mater. This program was eventually developed. He returned in 1959 to U.Va. as an Associate Professor of Medicine. From 1961 to 1966 he was the director of the Hematology Training Program and physician-in-charge of the Hematology Clinic. He served as director of the Harvey E. Jordan Research Laboratory where he studied red cell development and aging.
Dr. Thorup left U.Va. in 1966 to take a position at the University of Arizona's future medical school as professor and chair of the Department of Medicine. He worked with Merlin K. DuVal, M.D., and Philip Krutsch, M.D. as a three-man planning team developing a curriculum and interfacing with architects. While in Arizona, Dr. Thorup became particularly interested in the development of agencies that could guide and promote programs to increase equal access to health care and increase the general quality of health care while reducing cost by better management in planning. He was a proponent of communities correcting their own problems rather than having federal government involvement. While in Arizona, he was part of the Health Planning Council for Greater Tucson, Southern Arizona Health Association, Arizona Heart Association, Pima County Medical Society, Arizona Medical Association, and the Red Cross. Dr. Thorup's papers related to his time at the University of Arizona are at the University of Arizona.
In 1972 Dr. Thorup took a sabbatical from the University of Arizona and returned to Oxford, England. He worked with Dr. Alan Sharp and focused again on the problems of blood coagulation. He visited schools in Finland, Norway, and Sweden. He resumed his chairmanship of the Department of Medicine upon returning to Tucson and then relocated back to the University of Virginia in 1974 where he initiated a new program in continuing education. He became director of the Program of Human Biology and Society, and with Dr. James Childress began a medical ethics program. He also headed the Medical Center Hour, a weekly public conference on cultural and ethical issues related to health care. He retired in 1989 as Professor Emeritus of Medicine.
Dr. Thorup was a Diplomate of the American Board of Internal Medicine and a Fellow of the American College of Physicians as well as a member of the American Clinical and Climatological Association, American Federation for Clinical Research, American Medical Association, American Society of Hematology, International Society of Hematology, and Southern Society of Clinical Research. He also served on a number of groups in the state of Virginia. He was on the Board of Directors of the Virginia Association of Continuing Education of Health Professions and served as Chairman of the Council of Physician/Hospital Relations and Chairman of the Housestaff Education Committee. He was a member of the University's Health Systems Agency and Sub-Area Council, the Alumni Faculty Committee of the U.Va. Medical Alumni Association, and the Albemarle County Medical Society.
He wrote a widely used textbook, Fundamentals of Clinical Hematology, with Byrd S. Leavell, M.D. The first edition was published in 1960; the fifth and last in 1987. Most of his publications concerned internal medicine and hematology, but he also wrote papers on community health and medical education. He gave a talk comparing the founding of the University of Virginia Medical School with the University of Arizona Medical School. He did research related to Thomas Jefferson and his interest in medicine. The papers that Dr. Thorup collected concerning medicine and Jefferson are located at the Jefferson Library in Charlottesville, Virginia.
Outside of medicine, Dr. Thorup interests included painting; several of his works are hanging in the University of Virginia Claude Moore Health Sciences Library. On October 21, 2002, following a long illness, Dr. Thorup died at the University of Virginia Medical Center. He was married for 58 years to Barbara Turnbull Thorup and had three children, Cathryn Lynn, Todd Thorup, and Matthew Schuyler.
Scope and Content
The collection includes documents related to various editions of the Fundamentals of Clinical Hematology; U.Va. Class of 1944 and School of Medicine Class of 1946 reunions; letters and Thorup's notes concerning his 1959 visits to medical schools and hospitals in London, Utrecht and Groningan in the Netherlands, Uppsala and Goteborg in Sweden, Stockholm, Edinburgh, Oslo, and the University of St. Andrews in Scotland and consequently letters related to summer exchanges at schools abroad in 1960 through 1964; letters and notes concerning his 1972 visits to schools in Finland, Norway, and Sweden; letters received during 1958-59 at Oxford; and talks and papers related to pharmacologic anticoagulants, fibrinolysis, pulmonary embolism, the start of the University of Arizona Medical School, porphyrias, catalase, hemostasis, community medicine; and papers and schedules related to classes taught at U.Va. with James Childress on ethics and public policy in health care, plagues, and AIDS. The collection includes documents related to University of Virginia self-studies and visits to special libraries to obtain information and reprints concerning Thomas Jefferson and Jefferson's thinking on education and medicine..
Arrangement
The folders are in six boxes. The first box is a collection of Dr. Thorup's talks and papers arranged by date. The second box contains items related to UVa classes he taught with James Childress outside of the School of Medicine, also arranged by date. The third, fourth, and fifth boxes hold correspondence and documents arranged by date. The last box contains material related to Thorup's research about Thomas Jefferson and education and medicine.
Contents List
- "Purpura Due to Disorders of Platelet Function," [n.d.], TD (Box-folder 001-001)
  Abstract to College of Physicians
- Heparin, [n.d.], AD (Box-folder 001-002)
- "The Uptake of Radioactive iron by Human Bone Marrow in Vitro," [n.d.], TD with AN (Box-folder 001-003)
- "Hemoglobin J" by Oscar A. Thorup et. al., May 18, 1956, copy of journal article (Box-folder 001-004)
  Reprinted from Science, May 18, 1956.
- "The Rate of Removal of Iron from Culture Medium by Human Bone Marrow Suspension" and related letters, February-March 1958, 2 TLS, 1 TL copy, 1TD, photographs (Box-folder 001-005)
  Submitted and accepted for publication to The Journal of Laboratory and Clinical Medicine. One letter is from Thorup. The other two are from editors at the journal.
- The Identification and Rate of Migration of Erythrocyte Catalase on Starch Gel Electrophoresis, September 7-13, 1958, pamphlet (Box-folder 001-006)
  Proceedings of the VIIth International Congress of the International Society of Hematology
- "Possible Molecular Abnormality of Catalase in Erythrocytes in Homozygous Hemoglobin C Disease and Sickle Cell Anemia by Oscar A. Thorup, Jr., William E. Strole and Byrd S. Leavell with the technical ssistance of Mrs. Ralph Fitzwater, September 11, 1958, TD (Box-folder 001-007)
  Presented in part at the 7th Congress of the International Society of Hematology.
- "A Method for the Localization of Catalase on Starch Gels" by Oscar A. Thorup, Jr., William B. Strole, and Byrd S. Leavell, with the technical assistance of Florine Fitzwater and Helen Hughes, July 1961, Reprint (Box-folder 001-008)
  Reprint from The Journal of Laboratory and Clinical Medicine, Vol. 58, No., 1, July 1961.
- Catalase, a talk, 1962, Carbon copy of TD, AN, illustrations (Box-folder 001-009)
- "Human Erythrocyte Catalase: Demonstration of Heterogeneity and Relationship to Erythrocyte Aging in Vivo" by Oscar A. Thorup, Jr., and Johnson T. Carpenter, Jr., with the technical assistance of Mrs. Susan Leonard, November 1962, TD carbon copy (Box-folder 001-010)
  Presented in part at the Fifth Annual Session of the American Society of Hematology.
- "Human Erythrocyte Catalase: Demonstration of Heterogeneity and Relationship to Erythrocyte Ageing in Vivo" by O.A. Thorup, Junr., and J.T. Carpenter, and P. Howard, October 1964, Reprint (Box-folder 001-011)
  Reprinted from British Journal of Haematology, vol. 10, No. 4.
- "Events Affecting Research Administration, A New Proposal for Regulation," National Society for Medical Research, Vol. 4, No. 6., November 1964, Pamphlet (Box-folder 001-012)
  This issue is mainly addressing the use of laboratory animals.
- "A Stop-Dialysis Cup, December 1965-June 1966, TD, TD copy, TL, AN, photographs (Box-folder 001-013)
  Papers relate to the publication and patenting of the stop-dialysis cup.
- "Approach to Community Medicine" talk, April 17, 1966, December 10, 1966, TD with AN, AD (Box-folder 001-014)
- Erythrocytosis talk to T.M.C. [Tucson Medical Center] staff, May 11, 1966, AD (Box-folder 001-015)
- Hemostasis talk to Phoenix Surgical Society, May 11, 1966, AD (Box-folder 001-016)
- "Clinical Use of Blood Fractions: talk presented at the Academy of Medical Science of Maricopa County, November 1966, TD, TL carbon copy, postcard (Box-folder 001-017)
- List of papers presented from September 1966-April 1967, [1967], AD (Box-folder 001-018)
- "The Stethoscope" a talk, 1967, AD; journal article (Box-folder 001-019)
- "Medical Education and Community Health" talk, 1967, TD carbon copy (Box-folder 001-020)
  This talk was given to the American College of Physicians.
- "Medical Education and Community Health" by Oscar A. Thorup, September 1967, TD with AN, TD copy, journal article copy (Box-folder 001-021)
  Published in Arizona Medicine and prepared as a talk.
- Development of the schools of medicine at the University of Virginia and the University of Arizona, June 1971, TD copy (Box-folder 001-022)
  This was the feature talk at the 25th year reunion of the UVA SOM class of 1946.
- Development of the schools of medicine at the University of Virginia and the University of Arizona, June 1971, January 1972, TD with AN, TD with AN (copies), TD with AN (copies) with AN (Box-folder 001-023)
  Talk for the Annie Lipscomb lecture and also one given in Williamsburg.
- Fibrin experiments, 1972-73, AN (Box-folder 001-024)
- "Euthanasia," February 4, 1974, TD with AN, brochure (Box-folder 001-025)
  This talk was for the University of Arizona College of Medicine Division of Social Perspectives in Medicine seminar on "The Time of Death."
- Fibrinolysis, post 1976, TD with AN, AN (Box-folder 001-026)
  Includes talk, experiments, and pulmonary embolism information.
- Heparin, June 4, 1981, AD (Box-folder 001-027)
  Talk given at the University of Virginia.
- "The Porphyrias," August 4, 1984, TD with AN, An, slides, journal article (Box-folder 001-028)
- Pulmonary Embolism, February 28, 1985, TD and AN (Box-folder 001-029)
  Lecture given at the University of Virginia.
- Ethics and Public Policy in Health Care, GSAS 802, Spring 1988, spiral bound collection of papers (Box-folder 002-001)
  Instructors James Childress and Oscar Thorup, packet of readings for class published by Professor's Publishing, University of Virginia. Topics include the right to health care, cost containment, organ procurement and transplants, genetic screening.
- History of the plague starting in 546 AD, [1990?], AD (Box-folder 002-002)
  Notes are based on Scientific American article.
- Confronting Plagues, Religion 388, Spring 1990, TD, A drawings, AN, journal articles photocopied (Box-folder 002-003)
  Topics covered include the plague and AIDS.
- Plague in medieval Europe and AIDS, Religion 803, 1990, TD, journal articles photocopied (Box-folder 002-004)
  Topics covered include AIDS and the plague.
- Confronting Plagues, Religion 388, 1990-91, TD, journal articles photocopied (Box-folder 002-005)
  Topics covered include AIDS, the plague, and cholera.
- [Ethics and Public Policy in Health Care] Confronting Plagues, GSAS 802, 1991?, TD, journals, journal articles photocopied (Box-folder 002-006)
  Concerns AIDS.
- Confronting Plagues, Religion 388, Spring 1991, TD photocopied, AN (Box-folder 002-007)
  Instructors: James Childress and Oscar Thorup, tentative schedule of topics, students
- confronting Plagues, Religion 388, 1991, TD, journal articles photocopied, newspaper clippings, AN (Box-folder 002-008)
  Instructors: James Childress and Oscar Thorup; topic mostly covered is cholera, also "The Curious Case of Thyphoid Mary" by George A. Soper
- Correspondence: Demetrios A. Rigas, T.H.J. Huisman, and Oscar Thorup, May 7, 1956, September 27, 1956, TL copy (Box-folder 003-001)
- Correspondence: Truman G. Schnabel, Oscar Thorup, Seymour Farber, Carl-Bertel Laurell, George Ludwig, R.G. Macfarlane, November 1956-July 1957, TL, TL copies (Box-folder 003-002)
  Plans for a year abroad.
- Correspondence: from Barby Thorup to Oscar Thorup, November 9, 1956, AL with envelope (Box-folder 003-003)
- Correspondence: from Louis G. Welt to Oscar A. Thorup, October 1, 1957, TLs (Box-folder 003-004)
- Standards for Hospital Accreditation: Joint Commission on Accreditation of Hospitals, October 1, 1957, TMs (Box-folder 003-005)
- Correspondence: Oscar Thorup, Professor M. Torrioli, and Houston L. Bell, 1958, TL, TLs (Box-folder 003-006)
- Correspondence: concerning Oxford, 1958-59, TL, AL (Box-folder 003-007)
- Correspondence and travel notes: concerning London Hospital, 1958-59, TL, AL (Box-folder 003-008)
- Correspondence: from Barby Thorup to Oscar Thorup, February 7, 1958, AL, envelope (Box-folder 003-009)
- Correspondence: Letters from John L. Dusseau to Byrd Leavell, graduation photo, April-June 1958, TL copies (Box-folder 003-010)
  Correspondence concerns the book Fundamentals of Clinical Hematology. Dusseau comments on the organization of the book, carelessness, writing style and competitive situation but does offer to review the manuscript again after more work is done on it. June 1958 graduation photo of unidentified people.
- Correspondence: from Fancis L. Berkeley to Oscar Thorup, June 14, 1958, TL (Box-folder 003-011)
  The letter grants Thorus a leave of absence.
- "Thorup Will spend Year at Oxford," The Daily Progress June 21, 1958, newspaper clipping and copy (Box-folder 003-012)
- Thorup's salary compensation while on leave and household inventory, [June 1958], TD (Box-folder 003-013)
- Correspondence: family members, July 5, 1958-June 20, 1959, TL, AL (Box-folder 003-014)
  Included are newspaper clippings including one from The Washington Post and Times Herald, July 18, 1958, showing a school district map redrawn by the Charlottesville School Board to minimize desegregation.
- Correspondence: from tom Hunter and David E. Smith to the Thorups, July 1958, Tl, AL (Box-folder 003-015)
- Correspondence: Hugh R. Butt, Oscar Thorup, Joseph J. Bunim, David E. Smith, August 1958, TL (Box-folder 003-016)
  Topics include William E. Strole, medical school news, "public school situation" due to integration.
- Correspondence: from Tom Hunter to Oscar Thorup, September 29, 1958, TL (Box-folder 003-017)
  Topics include visit to Crispells, medical student withdrawals
- Correspondence: Barby and Oscar Thorup, Annie [Hunter], Julian R. Beckwith, Byrd {Leavell], October 1958, TL, AL (Box-folder 003-018)
  Includes medical school news.
- Correspondence: Oscar Thorup, William Parson, Tom Hunter, Byrd Leavell, Robert Q. Marston, H.B. Mulholland, Sheldon Zolna, November 1958, TL, AL (Box-folder 003-019)
  Includes medical school news, the book, and the [Charlottesville public] school integration with specific reference to its effect on faculty recruiting.
- Correspondence: Oscar Thorup, David E. Smith, Cecil Hoagie, Tom Hunter, O.B. Bobbitt, Cheves McC. Smythe, December 1958, TL, AL (Box-folder 003-020)
  Includes medical school news, public school integration, medical publication, Markle Scholars, financial support for planned trip [to look at other medical schools?].
- National Health Service Medical Cards for Barbara T. Thorup, Cathryn Lynn Thorup and Oscar A. Thorup, December 18, 1958, documents with AN and stamp (Box-folder 003-021)
- Correspondence: Oscar Thorup, Bill [William E. Strole], Andrew H., Tom Hunter, Bill [Jordan], William B. Herring, Byrd Leavell, Arthur Ebbert, January 1959, TL, AL (Box-folder 003-022)
  Includes medical school news, public school integration, Student Health, School of Medicine curriculum, the book, opportunity to visit European medical schools.
- Correspondence: concerning visit to Utrecht, The Netherlands, January 19, 1959, TL with AN (Box-folder 003-023)
- Correspondence and travel notes: concerning the University of Sheffield, January 13-February 26, 1959, TL, AN (Box-folder 003-024)
- General Information Regarding the Survey of a Medical School by Representatives of the Council on Medical Education and Hospitals, American Medical Association and the Executive Council of the Association of American Medical Colleges, January 26, 1959 (Box-folder 003-025)
- Correspondence: Louis G. Welt, Bill [William E. Strole], Audrey, Tom Hunter, Gordon Meiklejohn, February 1959, TL, AL (Box-folder 003-026)
  Includes Thorup's election to the Southern Society for clinical research, School of Medicine news, offer of a position at the University of Colorado Medical School.
- Correspondence and travel notes: concerning Uppsala, Goteborg, Sweden, February-December 1959, Tl, AL (Box-folder 003-027)
- Correspondence and travel notes: concerning visit to State University at Groningen, The Netherlands, February 25-June 1959, TL (Box-folder 003-028)
- Correspondence: Oscar Thorup, Bill [William E. Strole], David E. Smith, Annie [Hunter], G. Watson-James, Byrd Leavell, John L. Dusseau, W. Sidney Lowry, Barby thorup, Cecil Hougie, March 1959, TL, AL (Box-folder 003-029)
  Includes School of Medicine news, possibility of [Edgar] Shannon [coming to UVa as President], the Smith's basement no longer being used as a school, integration supposed to start up in September 1959, membership in the Southern Society for Clinical Research, the book, "UVa oudid Princeton" by electing an unknown, young cultural Rotarian as President. Quite a shock!" and Leavell's comments about the book.
- Correspondence: Byrd Leavell to Oscar Thorup, April 1959, TL, AL (Box-folder 003-030)
  Topics include the book and the catalase paper.
- Correspondence and travel notes: concerning visit to Stockholm, 1959, TL, AL (Box-folder 003-031)
- Correspondence and travel notes: concerning visit to Edinburgh University Medical School, 1959, TL, AN (Box-folder 003-032)
- Correspondence and travel notes: concerning visit to Oslo, Norway, 1959, TL, AN (Box-folder 003-033)
- Correspondence and travel notes: concerning visit to St. Andrews, Dundee, Scotland, 1959, TL, AL, AN (Box-folder 003-034)
- Correspondence: Summer exchange Case Western Reserve University 1959, October 1959, TL (Box-folder 003-035)
- Correspondence: Oscar Thorup, Roderick Heffron, Virgil C. Scott, March 1960, TL (Box-folder 003-036)
  Topics include visits to medical schools in Scandinavia and England to facilitate future exchanges of medical students and faculty.
- "A Guide to the New Facilities, University of Virginia Hospital, Charlottesville, Virginia," December 3, 1960, Pamphlet (Box-folder 003-037)
  Includes floor plans.
- Manual for the Institutional Self-Study and Periodic Visitation Program - Commission on Colleges and Universities, Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, 1960, 1960, Manual with AN (Box-folder 003-038)
- Correspondence: Summer Exchange Copenhagen for 1960, 1960, TL, AN (Box-folder 003-039)
- Correspondence: Summer Exchange Edinburgh for 1960, November 1959, TL (Box-folder 003-040)
- Correspondence: Summer Exchange London for 1960, 1959-1960, TL, AL (Box-folder 003-041)
- Correspondence: Summer Exchange Manchester for 1960, 1960, TL, AL (Box-folder 003-042)
- Correspondence: Summer Exchange Oxford for 1960, 1959-1960, TL, AL (Box-folder 003-043)
- Reports of trips to England, [1960?], TD (Box-folder 003-044)
- Correspondence: Summer Exchange Copenhagen for 1961, 1961, TL (Box-folder 004-001)
- Correspondence: Summer Exchange Dundee Scotland, University of St. Andrews for 1961, 1961, TL (Box-folder 004-002)
- Correspondence: Summer Exchange London for 1961, 1961-1962, TL (Box-folder 004-003)
- Correspondence: Summer Exchange Newcastle Upon Tyne for 1961, 1961, TL, AN (Box-folder 004-004)
- Daily Progress: University of Virginia Hospital, April 14, 1961, newspaper clippings photocopies (Box-folder 004-005)
- Hospital utilization statistics and notes, 1961-1964, TD (Box-folder 004-006)
- Summer exchange: Braunschweig, Germany for 1962, 1961-1962, TL (Box-folder 004-007)
- Southern Association of Colleges and Schools Constitution of the Association and Standards for Colleges, November 29, 1962, pamphlet (Box-folder 004-008)
- Summer exchange: University of Durham at Newcastle upon Tyne for 1962,1962, TL, AL (Box-folder 004-009)
- Summer exchange: Johns Hopkins for 1962,1962, TL (Box-folder 004-010)
- Summer exchange: London for 1962, 1962, TL, AL (Box-folder 004-011)
- Summer exchange: London, University of Durham, University of Virginia for 1962, 1962, TL, newsclippings (Box-folder 004-012)
- Summer exchange for 1962, 1962-1963, TL (Box-folder 004-013)
- Public Relations Committee, December 12, 1962, TL (Box-folder 004-014)
- Correspondence: concerning the Summer Student Exchange for 1963, 1962-64, 1978, TL, AL, photos (Box-folder 004-015)
  David B. Rice and Phillip J. Walker to University of Durham Medical School, Kings college, Newcastle upon Tyne; thomas Lanier to London Hospital Medical College; Genevieve Scarisbrick from University of Manchester Medical School.
- Memo from Dr. Moreland, Director of the Vivarium, to Oscar A. Thorup, [1963], T memo (Box-folder 004-016)